Finding Aid for Paul Blanshard Papers, 1912-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Writings and related materials circa 1917-1978
  - Background Files for Books/Post-Publication Materials
    - Democracy and Empire in the Caribbean (1947)
      - Reports to State Department March 9, 1943-May 19, 1945 (Box 11)
        [11-1]
      - Pre-book writings on Caribbean commenting on general causes of discontent in the area (Box 11)
        [11-2]
      - General topics and memoranda (Box 11)
        [11-3]
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 11)
        [11-4]
      - Reviews (Box 11)
        [11-5]
      - Scrapbook of reviews (Box 11)
        [11-6]
      - The official correspondence, memoranda, and reports of Paul Blanshard, Consultant, United States Section, Anglo-American Caribbean Commission 1942-1946 (Box 11)
      - Social and political forces in dependent areas of the Caribbean 1944 Part I (Box 11)
      - Social and political forces in dependent areas of the Caribbean 1944 (Box 11)
        (Part II and Part III, in one volume)
    - American Freedom and Catholic Power 1949
      - Bibliography (Box 12)
        [12-1]
      - Chapter 1: Prologue (Box 12)
        [12-2]
      - Chapter 2: How the Hierarchy Works, 5 folders (Box 12)
        [12-3, etc.-12-7]
      - Chapter 3: Church, State and Democracy, 2 folders (Box 12)
        [12-8; 12-9]
      - Chapter 4: Education and the Catholic Mind, 3 folders (Box 12)
        [12-10; 12-11; 12-12]
      - Chapter 5: Public Schools and Public Money (Box 12)
        [12-13]
      - Chapter 6: The Church and Medicine (Box 12)
        [12-14]
      - Chapter 7: Sex, Birth Control and Eugenics, 3 folders (Box 12)
        [12-15; 12-16; 12-17]
      - Chapter 8: Marriage, Divorce and Annulment, 3 folders (Box 12)
        [12-18; 12-19; 12-20]
      - Chapter 9: Censorship and Boycott, 7 folders (Box 12)
        [12-21, etc.-12-27]
      - Chapter 10: Science, Scholarship and Superstition, 2 folders (Box 12)
        [12-28; 12-29]
      - Chapter 11: Fascism, Communism and Labor (Box 12)
        [12-30]
      - Chapter 12: The Catholic Plan for America (Box 12)
        [12-31]
      - Chapter 13: Tolerance, Appeasement and Freedom, 2 folders (Box 12)
        [12-32; 12-33]
      - Chapter 13: Tolerance, Appeasement and Freedom, 3 folders (Box 13)
        [13-1; 13-2; 13-3]
      - Newspaper articles about book (Box 13)
        [13-4]
      - Reviews, 4 folders (Box 13)
        [13-5, etc.-13-8]
      - Foreign reviews, 3 folders (Box 13)
        [13-9; 13-10; 13-11]
      - Reviews from religious press (Box 13)
        [13-12]
      - Advisory Criticism (Box 13)
        [13-13]
      - Sermons based on or about book, 4 folders (Box 13)
        [13-14, etc.-13-17]
      - Promotional campaign, 2 folders (Box 13)
        [13-18; 13-19]
      - Sales ratings (Box 13)
        [13-20]
      - The Nation ban, 5 folders (Box 13)
        [13-21, etc.-13-25]
      - New York Times controversy (concerning advertising for book) (Box 13)
        [13-26]
      - Controversy: Cardinal Spellman vs Eleanor Roosevelt (Box 13)
        [13-27]
      - Controversy: Blanshard vs Francis J. Connell, C.S.S.R. (Box 13)
        [13-28]
      - Controversy: Blanshard vs James M. O'Neill, 3 folders (Box 13)
        [13-29; 13-30; 13-31]
      - 1958 edition reviews, 2 folders (Box 13)
        [13-32; 13-33]
      - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
        [14-1]
    - Communism, Democracy and Catholic Power (1952)
      - Reviews, 9 folders (Box 14)
        [14-2,etc.-14-10]
      - Promotional campaign (Box 14)
        [14-11]
      - Sales Ratings, 3 folders (Box 14)
        [14-12; 14-13; 14-14]
    - The Irish and Catholic Power (1954)
      - Bibliography (Box 14)
        [14-15]
      - Outline and Introduction (Box 14)
        [14-16]
      - Forward and Chapter 1: Perspective and Purpose (Box 14)
        [14-17]
      - Chapter 2: Past and Present, 2 folders (Box 14)
        [14-18; 14-19]
      - Chapter 3: Progress and Poverty, 2 folders (Box 14)
        [14-20; 14-21]
      - Chapter 4: The Clerical Republic, 7 folders (Box 14)
        [14-22, etc.-14-28]
      - Chapter 5: Censorship-Official and Unofficial, 5 folders (Box 15)
        [15-1, etc.-15-5]
      - Chapter 6: Segregated Education, 6 folders (Box 15)
        [15-6, etc.-15-11]
      - Chapter 7: Sex, Chastity and Population, 5 folders (Box 15)
        [15-12, etc. 15-16]
      - Chapter 8: Fanaticism and Moral Childhood, 6 folders (Box 15)
        [15-17, etc.-15-22]
      - Chapter 9: Northern Ireland and Partition, 13 folders (Box 15)
        [15-23, etc.-15-35]
      - Chapter 10: The Irish Catholic Empire Abroad, 6 folders (Box 16)
        [16-1, etc. 16-6]
      - Chapter 11: The Future of Irish Catholic Power (Box 16)
        [16-7]
      - Appendix: The Case of the Papal Nuncio, 5 folders (Box 16)
        [16-8, etc.-16-12]
      - Interviews (Box 16)
        [16-13]
      - Corrections, including supplemental bulletin (Box 16)
        [16-14]
      - The Commonweal controversy (Box 16)
        [16-15]
      - Promotional campaign (Box 16)
        [16-16]
      - Reviews, 8 folders (Box 16)
        [16-17, etc.-16-24]
      - "Two Faces of Ireland", 2 folders (Box 16)
        [16-25; 16-26]
      - Post-publication materials, 5 folders (Box 16)
        [16-27, etc.-16-31]
    - The Right to Read (1955)
      - Bibliography (Box 17)
        [17-1]
      - Chapter 1: The Great Literary Machine, 3 folders (Box 17)
        [17-2; 17-3; 17-4]
      - Chapter 2: Pattern of Control, 2 folders (Box 17)
        [17-5; 17-6]
      - Chapter 3: Communism and Capitalism, 2 folders (Box 17)
        [17-7; 17-8]
      - Chapter 4: Textbooks and the Schools, 3 folders (Box 17)
        [17-9; 17-10; 17-11]
      - Chapter 5: Patriotism and Treason, 5 folders (Box 17)
        [17-12, etc.-17-16]
      - Chapter 6: Sex and Obscenity, 3 folders (Box 17)
        [17-17; 17-18; 17-19]
      - Chapter 7: Pressure, Puritans and The Press, 2 folders (Box 17)
        [17-20; 17-21]
      - Chapter 8: Blasphemy, Faith and Race (Box 17)
        [17-22]
      - Chapter 9: Crime, Violence and the Comics, 6 folders (Box 17)
        [17-23, etc.-17-28]
      - Chapter 10: Advertising, Libel and Secrecy, 6 folders (Box 17)
        [17-29, etc.-17-34]
      - Chapter 11: The Future of Censorship, 2 folders (Box 17)
        [17-35; 17-36]
      - General, 5 folders (Box 17)
        [17-37, etc.-17-41]
      - Promotional campaign (Box 18)
        [18-1]
      - Reviews (Box 18)
        [18-2]
      - Original manuscript (Box 18)
        [18-3]
      - Scrapbook of reviews (Box 18)
    - God and Man in Washington (1960)
      - Chapter 2: One Nation Under God, 10 folders (Box 19)
        [19-1, etc.-19-10]
      - Chapter 3: God, Man, and the Supreme Court, 4 folders (Box 19)
        [19-11, etc.-19-14]
      - Chapter 4: God, Man and Congress, 2 folders (Box 19)
        [19-15; 19-16]
      - Chapter 5: God, Man and the Presidency, 7 folders (Box 19)
        [19-17, etc.-19-23]
      - Chapter 6: Pluralism and the Good Society, 2 folders (Box 19)
        [19-24; 19-25]
      - Promotional campaign (Box 19)
        [19-26]
      - Reviews (Box 19)
        [19-27]
      - Scrapbook of reviews (Box 19)
      - Original manuscript (Box 20)
        [20-1]
      - Materials collected by Blanshard concerning John F. Kennedy and his presidential campaign 1956-1960
        - General materials, 5 folders (Box 20)
          [20-2, etc.-20-6]
        - The Convention, 6 folders (Box 20)
          [20-7, etc.-20-12]
        - The Campaign, 10 folders (Box 20)
          [20-13, etc.-20-22]
        - West Virginia primary (Box 20)
          [20-23]
        - Wisconsin primary (Box 20)
          [20-24]
        - Kennedy's Houston speech (Box 20)
          [20-25]
        - Kennedy's education policy (Box 20)
          [20-26]
        - Richard Nixon's campaign (Box 20)
          [20-27]
        - Puerto Rico (Box 20)
          [20-28]
        - Kennedy administration (Box 20)
          [20-29]
    - Freedom and Catholic Power in Spain and Portugal (1962)
      - Bibliography and general information, 3 folders (Box 21)
        [21-1; 21-2; 21-3]
      - Chapter 1: Personal Prologue: An American Issue (Box 21)
        [21-4]
      - Chapter 2: From the Inquisition to Franco, 6 folders (Box 21)
        [21-5, etc.-21-10]
      - Chapter 3: A Political Church at Work, 3 folders (Box 21)
        [21-11; 21-12; 21-13]
      - Chapter 4: The Protestants, 8 folders (Box 21)
        [21-14, etc.-21-21]
      - Chapter 5: The Masons and the Jews (Box 21)
        [21-22]
      - Chapter 6: Sex, Marriage and Burial (Box 21)
        [21-23]
      - Chapter 7: Education in the Shadow of the Church, 3 folders (Box 21)
        [21-24; 21-25; 21-26]
      - Chapter 8: How the Censorship Works, 7 folders (Box 21)
        [21-27, etc. 21-33]
      - Chapter 9: The Labor-Capital Strait Jacket, 3 folders (Box 21)
        [21-34; 21-35; 21-36]
      - Chapter 10: Unholy Alliance, 4 folders (Box 22)
        [22-1, etc.-22-4]
      - Chapter 12: Catholics, Protestants and Fatima, 5 folders (Box 22)
        [22-5, etc.-22-9]
      - Notebooks of interviews and background information (Box 22)
        [22-10]
      - Reviews, 2 folders (Box 22)
        [22-11; 22-12]
    - Religion and the Schools (1963)
      - Outlines bibliography and introduction (Box 23)
        [23-a]
      - Chapter 1: Jefferson to Kennedy: The Continuing Controversy, 2 folders (Box 23)
        [23-1; 23-2]
      - Chapter 2: The Supreme Court Examines a New York Prayer, 2 folders (Box 23)
        [23-3; 23-4]
      - Chapter 3: The National Reaction (Box 23)
        [23-5]
      - Chapter 4: Is the Supreme Court Right?, 2 folders (Box 23)
        [23-6; 23-7]
      - Chapter 5: Bible-Reading and the Lord's Prayer in the Public Schools, 3 folders (Box 23)
        [23-8; 23-9; 23-10]
      - Chapter 6: Tax Dollars for Church Schools, 22 folders (Box 23)
        [23-11, etc.-23-32]
      - Chapter 7: Buses, Books and Teachers, 8 folders (Box 24)
        [24-1, etc. 24-8]
      - Chapter 8: Truth and Consequences, 2 folders (Box 24)
        [24-9; 24-10]
      - Appendices: Important legal cases regarding prayer, Bible-reading, and church-state relations, 6 folders (Box 24)
        [24-11, etc.-24-16]
      - Reviews, 2 folders (Box 24)
        [24-17; 24-18]
      - Scrapbook of Reviews and promotional materials (Box 24)
    - Paul Blanshard on Vatican II (1966)
      - Chapter 1: What was This Council?, 5 folders (Box 25)
        [25-1, etc. 25-5]
      - Chapter 2: John and the Beginning, 3 folders (Box 25)
        [25-6; 25-7; 25-8]
      - Chapter 3: Paul, the Institutional Man, 4 folders (Box 25)
        [25-9, etc.-25-12]
      - Chapter 4: Collegiality to Infallibility, 7 folders (Box 25)
        [25-13, etc.-25-19]
      - Chapter 5: Religious Liberty, External, 5 folders (Box 25)
        [25-20, etc.-25-24]
      - Chapter 6: Religious Liberty, Internal, 7 folders (Box 25)
        [25-25, etc.-25-31]
      - Chapter 7: The Jews, 6 folders (Box 25)
        [25-32, etc. 25-37]
      - Chapter 8: How Much Christian Unity?, 11 folders (Box 26)
        [26-1, etc. 26-11]
      - Chapter 9: Mary, Scripture and Tradition, 2 folders (Box 26)
        [26-12; 26-13]
      - Chapter 10: Sex, Celibacy and Women (Box 26)
        [26-14]
      - Chapter 11: Marriage and Divorce, 5 folders (Box 26)
        [26-15, etc.-26-19]
      - Chapter 12: Birth Control and So Forth, 7 folders (Box 26)
        [26-20, etc.-26-26]
      - Chapter 13: The Miraculous Underworld, 3 folders (Box 26)
        [26-27; 26-28; 26-29]
      - Chapter 14: Church, State and Diplomacy, 4 folders (Box 26)
        [26-30, etc.-26-33]
      - Chapter 15: Church, State and Schools, 2 folders (Box 26)
        [26-34; 26-35]
      - Chapter 16: Sweetness and Light, 4 folders (Box 26)
        [26-36, etc.-26-39]
      - Chapter 17: Balance Sheet, 2 folders (Box 26)
        [26-40; 26-41]
      - Background materials and general information on Vatican collected and organized by Blanshard (Box 27)
        - Second Session, First Week, 2 folders (Box 27)
          [27-1; 27-2]
        - Second Session, Second Week (Box 27)
          [27-3]
        - Second Session, Third Week (Box 27)
          [27-4]
        - Second Session, Fourth Week (Box 27)
          [27-5]
        - Second Session, Fifth Week (Box 27)
          [27-6]
        - Second Session, Sixth Week (Box 27)
          [27-7]
        - Second Session, Seventh Week, 2 folders (Box 27)
          [27-8; 27-9]
        - Second Session, Eighth Week (Box 27)
          [27-10]
        - Second Session, Ninth Week (Box 27)
          [27-11]
        - Second Session, Tenth Week (Box 27)
          [27-12]
        - Second Session, Eleventh Week (Box 27)
          [27-13]
        - Second Session, Twelfth Week, 2 folders (Box 27)
          [27-14; 27-15]
        - Third Session, 5 folders (Box 27)
          [27-16, etc.-27-20]
        - Fourth Session, First. Week (Box 27)
          [27-21]
        - Fourth Session, Second to Fifth Weeks (Box 27)
          [27-22]
        - Fourth Session, Sixth to Eighth Weeks (Box 27)
          [27-23]
        - General Information, 4 folders (Box 27)
          [27-24, etc. 27-27]
      - Vatican Decrees, 3 folders (Box 28)
        [28-1; 28-2; 28-3]
      - Post-Vatican Council (Box 28)
        [28-4]
      - Reviews, 3 folders (Box 28)
        [28-5; 28-6; 28-7]
    - Personal and Controversial (1973)
      - Reviews, 3 folders (Box 28)
        [28-8; 28-9; 28-10]
    - Some of My Best Friends are Christians (1974)
      - Reviews (Box 28)
        [28-11]
  - Background materials used in preparation of speeches, articles, etc.
    - Birth Control, 9 folders (Box 7)
      [7-1, etc.-7-9]
    - Catholic Church Land Possessions (Box 7)
      [7-10]
    - Catholicism and the Presidency (Box 7)
      [7-11]
    - Federal Aid to Private Schools (Box 7)
      [7-12]
    - Mixed religious marriages (Box 7)
      [7-13]
    - Papal Election 1959 (Box 7)
      [7-14]
    - Parochiaid, 3 folders (Box 7)
      [7-15; 7-16; 7-17]
    - Right Wing, 3 folders (Box 7)
      [7-18; 7-19; 7-20]
    - Vatican Ambassador (Box 7)
      [7-21]
    - Vermont School System and Religious Instruction (Box 7)
      [7-22]
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Information series is noteworthy for the clippings and scrapbooks maintained by Blanshard throughout his career. This series will be most valuable for its documentation of early Blanshard activities that are not otherwise represented in the collection.
  - Books and Pamphlets on Paul Blanshard
    - Francis J. Connell, C.S.S.R. Scholarship and Paul Blanshard (n.d.) and Blanshard's reply, Father Connell and The (Box 7)
    - Scholarship of Paul Blanshard (Box 7)
    - Frances J. Connell, C.S.S.R. Paul Blanshard: American Freedom and Catholic Power, 1950 (Box 7)
    - Answers to American Freedom and Catholic Power (Box 7)
    - Dale Francis American Freedom and Paul Blanshard (1950) [3 copies] and Answering Paul Blanshard, 2 copies (Box 7)
    - George H. Dunne, S.J. Religion and American Democracy (1949), 3 copies (Box 7)
    - Blanshard and His Sponsors (1951) (Box 7)
    - James M. O'Neill Catholicism and American Freedom (1952) (Box 7)
  - Books and Pamphlets on religious themes, some including comments by or about Blanshard
    - Awful Disclosures of Maria Monk [1836) (Box 7)
    - Martin J. Scott, S.J ., Science Helps the Church: The Church Favors Science (Box 7)
    - Protestants and other Americans United for Separation of Church and State Studies in Church-State Relations: The American Way (Box 7)
    - George Earle Owen Faith and Freedom (1953) (Box 7)
    - Edward C. Podvin, M.D. A Doctor Speaks out on Birth Control (undated) (Box 7)
    - Vox Vocis Contraception is Sin (1949) (Box 7)
    - Joseph P. Kamp Famine in America: Home Grown by the Farmers from Union Square, 2 copies (Box 7)
    - Rt. Rev. Wm. C. McGrath, P.A. Fatima or World Suicide (1950) (Box 7)
    - Friends of Democracy, Inc. Joe Kamp: Peddler of Propaganda and Hero of the Pro-Fascists (undated) (Box 7)
    - The Future of Protestants and other Americans United for Separation of Church and State (1962) (Box 7)
    - Beacon Press. The Ideas and the Books (1964) (Box 7)
    - William Ebenstein Church and State in Franco-Spain (1960) (Box 7)
  - Clippings/scrapbooks (mainly about Paul Blanshard)
    - University of Michigan 1910-1914 (Box 8)
      [8-1]
    - Harvard University and Maverick Congregational Church (East Boston) 1914-1916 (Box 8)
      [8-2]
    - First Congregational Church (Tampa, Florida) 1916-1919 (Box 8)
      [8-3]
    - Amalgamated Textile Workers of America (Utica and Rochester New York) 1918-1923, 5 folders (Box 8)
      [8-4, etc.-8-8]
    - British Labor Movement 1923 (Box 8)
      [8-9]
    - League for Industrial Democracy 1924-1933 (Box 8)
      [8-10]
    - City Affairs Committee and Department of Investigation and Accounts, New York City
      - Papers 1931-1937, 3 folders (Box 8)
        [8-11; 8-12; 8-13]
      - Scrapbooks April 1931-April 1932 (Box 8)
      - Scrapbooks April 1932-July 1933 (Box 8)
      - Scrapbook 1 December 29, 1928-June 1, 1934 (Box 9a)
      - Scrapbook 1 (cont.) June 5, 1934-March 14, 1935 (Box 9b)
      - Scrapbook 2 March 14, 1935-December 19, 1935 (Box 9c)
      - Scrapbook 2 (cont.) December 20, 1935-September 18, 1936 (Box 9d)
      - Scrapbook 3 September 19, 1936-February 2, 1938 (Box 9e)
    - American Labor Party 1940 (Box 10)
      [10-1]
    - Miscellaneous 1942 (Box 10)
      [10-2]
    - Miscellaneous 1947 (Box 10)
      [10-3]
    - Miscellaneous 1948 (Box 10)
      [10-4]
    - Miscellaneous 1949, 3 folders (Box 10)
      [10-5; 10-6; 10-7]
    - Miscellaneous 1950, 5 folders (Box 10)
      [10-8, etc.-10-12]
    - The Nation ban, 1949-1950 (Box 10)
      [10-13]
    - The Vatican Holy Year 1950, 3 folders (Box 10)
      [10-14; 10-15; 10-16]
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1951, 7 folders (Box 10)
        [10-17, etc.-10-23]
      - 1952, 2 folders (Box 10)
        [10-24; 10-25]
      - 1953 (Box 10)
        [10-26]
      - 1954 (Box 10)
        [10-27]
      - The Commonweal controversy, 1954 (Box 10)
        [10-28]
      - 1955 (Box 10)
        [10-29]
      - America controversy, 1955 (Box 10)
        [10-30]
      - 1956-1974, 19 folders (Box 10)
        [1 folder for each year; 10-31, etc.-10-49]
  - Personal and miscellaneous
    - Biographical Information (Box 29)
      [29-1]
    - Genealogical Information including marriage certificate (Box 29)
      [29-2]
    - Miscellaneous family materials, including correspondence (Box 29)
      [29-3]
    - Materials related to Blanshard's Journey of Remembrance 1966 to the towns of his youth in Ohio, Michigan and Canada (also includes History of Fredericksburg, Ohio and Community) (Box 29)
      [29-4]
    - Miscellaneous materials related to Protestants and other Americans United for Separation of Church and State, 3 folders (Box 29)
      [29-5; 29-6; 29-7]
    - Brother Colin Macdonald, "Paul Blanshard and American Catholicism" 1969 (Box 29)
      M.A. thesis, University of San Francisco
    - Clayton LeRoy McNearney, "The Roman Catholic Response to the Writings of Paul Blanshard" 1970 (Box 29)
      Ph.D. Thesis, University of Iowa
  - Miscellaneous
    (materials received after the processing of the first accession)
    - Diaries and journal notes
      - 1939, 1946, 1948 (Box 29)
      - 1962-1967 (Box 29)
      - 1970s, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Articles, books, and newspaper column
      - Miscellaneous published articles 1973-1979 (Box 29)
      - Articles published in The Churchman, 1975-1977
        - "Saints Aren't Funny--Or Are They?" (Box 29)
        - "Catholicism and Sex" (Box 29)
        - "Sex and Those Celibate Fathers" (Box 29)
        - "Anti-Sexual Religion" (Box 29)
        - "Recalling Controversial Days" (Box 29)
      - Articles published in The Humanist, 1975-1976
        - "Humanism Versus Orthodoxy" (Box 29)
        - "Three Cheers for our Secular State" (Box 29)
      - Notes for a book, A Pocket Guide to Religion and Morals 1939 (Box 29)
      - Notes and correspondence for unpublished book, When Girls Were Good 1949-1952 (Box 29)
      - Reviews and excerpts of Classics of Free-Thought 1974-1978 (Box 29)
      - "My View," column in the St. Petersburg, Florida, Evening Independent 1975 (Box 29)
      - Miscellaneous writings undated (Box 29)
    - Speeches
      - Abortion February 28, 1971 (Box 29)
      - The Humanist Case Against Organized Religion November 8, 1974 (Box 29)
      - Humanism vs Orthodoxy April 25, 1975 (Box 29)
      - Religious and Anti-Religious Freedom October 5, 1975 (Box 29)
      - Separation of Church and State January 24, 1976 (Box 29)
    - Clippings 1972-1977
      - Various (Box 29)
- Sound Recordings
  The Sound Recording series consists of reel-to-reel tapes and phonograph discs. Included is a broadcast, May 16, 1960, of "Open Hearing" on ABC-TV news on the topic of the Catholic Church and the election of 1960 with guests, Paul Blanshard, James O'Gara, and John Bennett. There is, in addition, a recording of a speech, 1973, delivered before the Americans United for Separation of Church and State, entitled, "Our Battle with Clerical Power"; and disc recording of Blanshard appearing on WNEW's program "Counterpoint" moderated by William Kunstler.
  - Audio-tapes
    [Blanshared digital audio files are accessible only in the Bentley Library reading room.]
    - Our Battle with Clerical Power Dr. Paul Blanshard, 1973, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
      - [Side 1], [851649-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Speech given before the organization Americans United for Separation of Church and State.)
      - [Side 2], [851649-SR-1-2]; mp3 file; (Speech given before the organization Americans United for Separation of Church and State.)
    - "Open Hearing" and "Open Line", 1960 May 15, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [851649-SR-3-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion of John F. Kennedy's campaign, his Catholic religion, and other issues of Catholicism in the U.S., and a discussion of the separation of Church and State.)
    - Speech before Americans United for Separation of Church and State 1973 (Box 31)
  - Phono-discs
    - WNEW Counterpoint with William Kuntsler, 1 phonograph records (Box 1)
      (located with sound recordings)
    - "The Future of Catholic Power", 2 phonograph records (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series contains portraits of Blanshard and his three wives; photos of a demonstration at Macy's in 1949 over its refusal to sell American Freedom and Catholic Power. In addition there are family photographs and portraits of Norman Thomas. Blanshard was a supporter of Thomas in many of his elections.
  - Portraits
    - 1913 1916 (Box 31)
    - 1950s (Box 31)
    - 1960s-1970s (Box 31)
  - Paul Blanshard at various meetings of Blanshard family (Box 31)
    (include brother Brand Blanshard, grandparents, father, Francis George Blanshard, and sons Paul and Rufus Blanshard)
  - Julia Anderson Blanshard 1890s-1930s (Box 31)
  - Mary Hillyer Blanshard 1900s-1960s (Box 31)
  - Beatrice Mayer Blanshard 1962, 1970s (Box 31)
  - Blanshard homes: Thetford Center, Virginia and Washington D.C. (Box 31)
  - Thomas, Norman (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
    (include demonstration in 1949 outside of Macy's Department Store over their refusal to stock Blanshard's book)
- Julia Anderson Blanshard circa 1920-1939
  The papers of Julia Anderson Blanshard is small and consists of newspaper articles written by her in the 1920s and 1930s. Some of these detail her observations while visiting in the Soviet Union and of her visit to different nudist camps in Germany.